Hello, everyone. Today, I'll be solving with you the second question of sheet. I didn't
get to fully write the solution. I had a few sorrys in the solution during the tutorial,
so I will present the big proof. So we want to prove that multiplication is monotonic,
so that if a is equal to b, it's u, that, and d. So as I suggested in the tutorial,
we didn't have the type. That's why induction is not working. Now we have the type induction
works. So we have the base case where d is 0, and we have the step case. We have an induction
hypothesis. We have the same theorem statement applying for d, and you want to prove the
conclusion for d plus 1. And we have the two assumptions from our theorem statement applying
here to the successor of d. All right, so to finish the proof of the base case,
let me start with that one. So what is the base case? The base case is you have a smaller than
equal to b, c smaller than equal to 0, and I want to prove that. So the informal proof idea
would be, okay, if c is less than or equal to 0, then we can get that c is 0. And if c is 0,
then we know that a times c is 0, and b times, sorry, a times c is 0, and we know that 0 is
less than or equal to anything, so that would finish our proof. So let's try and do it that way.
So firstly, I'll just, as I said, conclude that c is 0. If something is smaller than or equal to 0,
then that thing is 0. So let's search for that. So we'll search for 0 that this x. So do we have
any theorems that are saying that? Are the results, for example? Is someone where, yeah,
so here, for example, this is exactly what we want. So we have an assumption that something
is less than or equal to 0, and from that, we conclude that that same variable is 0.
So I will take that theorem. So I have uploaded a proof on Keats, but I'm going to, perhaps,
do some slightly different steps here just to show you the range of possibilities. So here,
in the proof there, I did it with forward reasoning here. I'm doing it with backward
reasoning, for example. So here, we have a rule. So we go from the conclusion to the assumption,
and then we want to show that c is less than or equal to 0. So we can get that. I will just
call these assumptions, I'll call the base case assumptions or premises. I'll just call,
I'll get the many names. So I'll just call the base case. The base case assumptions are
two assumptions of our theorem, but one of them is for d equals 0. So I'll just take the second
one of those assumptions, and that precisely proves our goal. Second one, so you have this one,
we're using this one, and then we want to prove that one. So that's the first step.
The second step is to show that a times c is 0 because c is 0 itself. So let's find the theorem
that says that. If something is multiplied by 0, that thing equals 0. So that is called this.
So I'll just say from, so let me just 0. We'll do two substitutions first. I will substitute
this equation, equation number one, equality number one. So that would make a times 0,
0 for the 0, which is the value of the group. And then I will do a substitution with the theorem
that we have found out, and then we have that 0 equals 0. And we of course know that this is
trivially true, so we do two dots because this is an equality, and then we have proved it.
Now the last theorem we want to, the last thing we want to find out is that
a theorem that says that 0 is less than or equal to anything, right? And that is
precisely the theorem that we want. So here from that theorem, we want to conclude that
a times c is smaller than or equal to b times d. So let me just go here. So first of all,
I will substitute this value for a times c that I found out, that I just showed. And then now we have
a goal that says 0 is more than or equal to b less than b multiplied by 0. And that holds,
because we found that this theorem earlier, which says that 0 is more than or equal to anything.
And then if I just do a dot, Isabelle will be able to map this a to b times 0. And that
finishes the base case. The step case is slightly more that much, not very involved.
So to prove the step case, as I said in the tutorial, we do the following. We do it by
considering cases on the value of c. So we consider the case where the value of c equals
successor of d. And we consider the case where it's not equal to it. So if it is equal to d,
equals successor of d, then we have a separate proof for that case. And for the other case,
we also have a separate proof. So let me start with this case for that one. So we basically want
to show, here we want to show that a times c is more than or equal to b times successor of d.
So what I will do is the following. I'll substitute the value of c from the case
assumption that we have. So we have that c equals d. We assume that. So I'll substitute
that here. And then we have this. And we have this. And the second step, the next step, is to
show that this is less than or equal to that. From our assumptions, I will call this step case.
From the second assumption of the step case, we know that a is more than or equal to b.
If a is more than or equal to b, we know that a times sum anything will be more than
equal to b times anything. So we want to find a theorem that says that if we multiply two numbers,
if we have two numbers, let's say x and y, and we know that x is smaller than or equal to y,
and we also know that if we know that x is smaller than or equal to y, then we know that
x multiplied by something, some constant c, is going to be smaller than or equal to y multiplied
for any constant, of course. And that theorem we already have it. So we have here i is more than
or equal to j. That implies that i multiplied by any k is smaller than or equal to j multiplied by any k.
So that theorem is called nat dot mult l e mono. So let me just get that theorem there.
And the assumption that we want to use is step case case. So then now we have a theorem,
we have a fact, and we have something that we want to prove in the theorem,
and that thing that we want to prove is only an instantiation of the fact. So that finished
the first case where c is successively. The second case, which is more complicated,
we assume that c is not equal to successor of d. So from that we know,
so that tells us a few things. First of all, if c is not equal to d,
is not equal to the successor of d, then we have one fact. We know from that that
c is either smaller, is either greater than or equal, strictly greater than the successor of d,
because it's not equal to it, or the other possibility is that it is strictly smaller
than the successor of d. So we want to prove that. So we want to find a fact that says that if some
numbers are not equal, then the first number is strictly smaller than the second number
or the other round. So let me look up a theorem that says, okay, something is not equal. If
something else is strictly smaller than the same thing, one of them is strictly smaller.
So let's see what theorems we have there that talk about that. Yes. So this one shows what we want.
So this says that whenever you have two numbers not equal, you can substitute that term
with saying that the first number is strictly smaller or the second number is strictly smaller
than the other one. So let me use that theorem. So how can we use this theorem? So now this is
a substitution. So this is because this is an equality, this is not an implication,
you can only use that substitution, right? So we want to prove this and we already have that.
So how can we do it? We can substitute from the right to the left. So in order for you to use
a substitution from the right to the left, you add this word after the substitution rule
that you have. You add symmetric and that will reverse the direction of the equality.
So now you have the left hand side is that and the right hand side is that. And why did I do that?
It's because substitution only works from the left to the right. So now we'll apply
the substitution. It turned our goal into this, like it turned from this disjunction into this,
into the fact that C is not equal to D. Now we have in our case assumption that C is not equal
to D. But so let me just get it here using C not equal successor of D. So now we have this
and we want to show that. But I will try and use the dot, but it will not work. You know why?
Because the qualities are in the wrong directions. This is C is not equal to
suck D and suck D is not equal to C. So you can again reverse the direction of this inequality
by using symmetric again, the same keyword. So now we have suck D is not equal to C as your fact,
because we changed the order in which we flipped the equality in the fact.
And that's what we want to prove. So it works with the dot because they are exactly the same
thing. Okay. That's the first step. Now, okay, if I know that, and like now that I know that both
of those are, so one of those two cases is true, that adds some information to us. But in fact,
we also know something else, which is that C is strictly smaller than successor of D. Why is that?
Because from our assumptions in the step case, so the second, the third assumption here,
so you have the induction hypothesis first assumption, the second assumption, the second
assumption here says that it's smaller than equal to suck D. So B is strictly bigger than
successor of D. So we want to derive that it's indeed strictly smaller than successor of D.
So we want to find a theorem that says, so we want to, we want to firstly show that it's
like from this assumption of the step case, that it is indeed not the case that C is strictly greater
than the successor of D. We want to find a theorem basically that says that if something
is smaller than or equal, A is smaller than or equal to B, then we know that B is not smaller
than or equal to A. That theorem, for example, here, I'll just use this one. So this one
assumes if you know that X is smaller than or equal to Y, then you know that X cannot be
strictly smaller than Y. Take that theorem of step case. So now we, the step case three,
that assumption was the one that says that C is smaller than equal to D. So we can also prove
this. This is just forward reasoning. Now the third step would be to conclude, okay, now we
have that we have two facts that this or that C is strictly greater than the successor of D
or C is strictly smaller than successor of D. That, and we know that C is not strictly greater than
successor of D, that from those facts we should be able to conclude that C is strictly smaller
than successor of D. So how can we do that? We again need to find a theorem that says that
that basically says that if you have A, so what exactly do we have? We have A or B, let's say,
and so we have, that's the A and that's the B, and we have the negation of the A,
and we want to conclude that the B holds for that. So the negation, we want to conclude
that B is true for that, right? So let me just try and see if I can find it like this,
otherwise I will find, okay, so this is too difficult to find, so we'll just say,
okay, let's just write it B, so we want to put from that A, that B holds. Okay, so we found
exactly what we want, so we have some, for any P in Q, if P or Q hold, then we know that not P is
not P, then we can conclude that from that Q. Let me just take that, conclude that C is more than
equals, strictly smaller than successor of D using this theorem. That theorem has two assumptions,
the first assumption is the disjunction, so we can do it this way, and the second assumption is
that which we just have here, and then that gives us exactly the conclusion that we want,
so here we use a dot, then now the next step is to say, so recall,
so when you have a proof of a mathematical induction, what do we actually want?
Like the goal is to apply the induction hypothesis as a state in the large group tutorial, so
the induction hypothesis has in its assumption, in order for us to use the induction hypothesis
here, we have to have, we have to satisfy this assumption and that assumption. The second
assumption is that C is more than equal to D, which that should hold in our case now,
because we know that C is strictly smaller than D, so if it's strictly smaller than D,
then we know that it's smaller than equal to D. So from that we can, so we want to conclude,
we want to conclude that we are equal to D, so that we can use the induction hypothesis,
so now we want to find a theorem that says that if A is smaller than or equal, strictly smaller
than the successor of B, then that A is smaller than or equal to B. So do we have anything like
that in the right direction? Yeah, we have this one, we can use this, we have this one,
so we can use this. So this one is a substitution, it's gone because it's an equality, as you can see
here, it's not an implication, but you can use it. So we want to, so we have this as our goal,
I want to transform it into that, and then that we already have from fact number three.
So how can we do a substitution from right to left? As I stated earlier, we use symmetric,
and that will reverse the direction of the substitution, and then we can just say apply
substitution this rule, and then we have this, C is strictly smaller than successor of B,
and then you say using three, because that fact we have it already. Okay, so now we have this,
so the last step is to apply the induction hypothesis. So how do we apply the induction
hypothesis? So what do we want from the induction hypothesis? Let's just see.
So induction hypothesis can tell us that we can conclude from it that A times C is more than equal
to B times D, and then from that we know that A times C will also be smaller than equal to
B times successor of B. So let us firstly conclude that A times C is smaller than or equal to B
times D. So I would just say, so suck the IH, which we have renamed all of our
step-case assumptions, induction hypothesis and the two other assumptions, step-case.
So step-case of one now is induction hypothesis, and now we need two assumptions for it. The first
one is that A is smaller than or equal to B, and forward reasoning here, so that is assumption,
that is step-case assumption number two. The second thing, which is that C is smaller than
or equal to B, we have already proved it in step number four, and now we have our required
conclusion. And now the last step is to show that A times C is smaller than or equal to
B times successor of B. So here this is what we want, this is the goal that we want,
and now we want to find a theorem that says that if A is smaller than or equal to B,
then A, anything smaller than or equal to the line by that very same x, and that is called
less than or equal to 1. So here I will just this time do backward reasoning just to show you it.
So we need, we fact firstly need to show that B times, this is to show that B times D is smaller
than or equal to B times successor of D. Here we have the x as the first argument,
A is like an argument, because the x is, and the x and x here replaces the B,
and the A is the D, and the B is the successor of D. So we now need to show that D is smaller than
or equal to the successor of D. So how can we show that? So let's just show that on its own.
So let's just find theorems. A theorem says something, anything is smaller than or equal
to the successor of itself. Okay, we don't have that. We probably have something that says it's
strictly smaller, and that's the right one, yeah. From that we can in fact try to conclude that D
is smaller than the successor of D, and then from that we can conclude that D
is smaller than or equal to the successor of D, and for that we want a theorem that says if something
is smaller, something else, then it's the first theorem. So using that, six, this fact number
eight, we have it using seven. Okay, and now we have that B is more than equal to,
B times D is more than equal to B times successor of D, and at the same time we have
A times C is more than equal to B times D. So from those two facts we want to conclude that
the final, the thesis, which is our final conclusion, we want something, we want a theorem
basically that says that if X is smaller than equal to Y, and Y is smaller than equal to Z,
then from that we can conclude that smaller than or equal to Z. All right, and why do I do that?
Why do I want that? Because here the X is going to be B times D, and sorry, the X is going to be
A times C, and the Y is going to be B times D, and the Z is going to be B times successor of D.
So do we have any theorem that has that? So we have write it this way so that we narrow down a bit
the results. Yeah, okay, so we have the transitivity, and this is precisely what we need. So then we
can say using that theorem of, so what was the first fact? I think it was five, which is the result of
applying the induction hypothesis of five and eight. Right, and that precisely gives us, and basically
that's all. Thank you very much for watching this. I hope it's easier now that we have the
video here, which is a bit slower than the tutorial.